Empresses in the Palace—the Legend of Zhen Huan
Adopted from the novel by Liu Lian Zi
[to join mailing list] carsenwei@yahoo.com
[to sponsor translators] liberapay.com/ZHZSubbers
Theme: Unfortunate Love
Perturbed by the thoughts on my mind
no matter how hard I try to sever my love.
I could give away my crown for the beauty by my side,
but the wheel of fortune turns weals into woes,
and woes into weals.
No one is the master of their own destiny,
the vicissitudes throughout their life.
For all the lovers in the world,
who can break the spell of romance?
I could give away my crown for the beauty by my side,
but the wheel of fortune turns weals into woes,
and woes into weals.
No one is the master of their own destiny,
the vicissitudes throughout their life.
For all the lovers in the world,
who can break the spell of romance?
Who can break the spell of romance?
[to join mailing list] carsenwei@yahoo.com
[to sponsor translators] liberapay.com/ZHZSubbers
But it all started because of you.
Lingrong wasn't involved in this.
Even so, she had Yu strangled in the Cold Palace.
That is not the sensitive girl I know.
Even a cornered rabbit bites.
But she settled something that
even put Su Peisheng at a loss.
That was very much to my surprise.
Lingrong did it for us, regardless.
She did, but I can't help thinking
that she's not the person we know.
She's finally dead?
Completely and utterly.
Someone saw her corpse
being thrown into the plague pit.
Her neck was half torn.
It was so frightful.
The castrated did know how to use a knife.
But that's not a surprise,
for her offending His Majesty's servants.
It serves her well.
Did she divulge anything?
Not a single word.
Good for her.
We underestimated that sickly Zhen Huan.
We'll wait and see.
It's about to rain after all the stuffiness.
Jinxi.
My Lady, what are you awake?
I feel alarmed.
The tales of supernatural existence
are simply repeated fictions.
Don't take them to heart.
I'm not afraid of ghosts.
I'm afraid that ...
Yu's death does not bring this matter to an end.
My Lady, do you suspect that
someone else was behind this.
With hindsight, Yu was not
a person with a scheming mind.
How did she learn medicine as a maid?
Not only did she know about the dosage,
but she could also coordinate with my servants.
And how did she get the medicine?
True.
We should have kept her alive for interrogation.
She hated me to the marrow.
She wouldn't say a thing.
She might even accuse us of slander.
Now that she's dead,
the people behind her would lower their guard
and we will have a chance to trace them.
If so, let us put on a show about Yu's death.
A ghost ... A ghost!
Are we almost home?
Yes, My Lady.
My Lady, you must be tired after offering prayers
at the Baohua Hall all night.
The Empress has been suffering from cephalalgia.
It is a concubine's duty to wish Her Majesty well.
Who's crying?
It sends chills down my spine.
Go faster!
A ghost ... There's a ghost!
A ghost!
Did you really see it?
Lady Fuca, you had been praying all night.
Did that cause you sudden blurred vision?
Ask Sang'er if you don't believe me.
She saw it too.
I did ... it was the long hair of a woman
cold as ice ...
and the stench ... of a dead body ...
See? Sang'er is scared out of her wits.
She is the smartest maid of mine.
I heard that a eunuch saw it s well.
Now he looks like death warmed over.
I really saw it ...
in a white dress ... her face pale as death ...
sticking out a long tongue ... with blood dripping ...
and blood dripping from her eyes too ...
Her hair was disarranged ... and she kept crying ...
Is it because she died in grievance
that she kept crying?
You do hit the nail on the head when you talk.
Why would she cry around midnight otherwise?
Died in grievance?
(gasp) It must be Yu who died in the Cold Palace.
She turned into a vengeful ghost.
Don't say that. She ought to
die a thousand deaths for her offence.
What do you know?
She was resisting suicide
and that was causing trouble to Mr Su.
So they strangled her with a bowstring.
The harem is now in chaos.
Shall we report to His Majesty when he returns?
His Majesty is averse to superstitions.
You should tell him if you dare to.
"There is a debtor for every debt."
I owe nothing to her!
Why did she came to me?
That is why she went away
without doing anything to you.
Otherwise, you wouldn't be sitting here right now.
So, who do you think Yu is coming after?
Not Sourire anyway.
I heard that Lady Sourire is
having trouble sleeping after Yu's death.
Did she see the doctors?
Thank Your Highness for your concern.
Dr Wen has been tending her.
But she showed no sign of improvement.
The palace is frequented by a ghost.
Over a dozen people have seen it in succession.
We can't go a day without being disturbed.
I heard that a few eunuchs were bed-ridden because of that
and Lady Fuca doesn't have the nerve to even step out of her chamber.
His Majesty believes that ghost stories
are told by the unintelligent minds.
With so many self-proclaimed witnesses,
the story was relayed through repeated embellishment.
It must have been so long since His Majesty's last visit
that Consort Astuce has forgot what he said.
You Highness gets to see His Majesty frequently,
unlike us leading a lonely existence in the palace.
The rumors wouldn't spread
if we all are as blessed as Your Highness.
Unfortunately, we are not.
Pray for blessing while you can,
or even the Buddha can't save you
when the ghosts comes.
I don't want to hear the nonsensical stories
that you tell in private ever again.
I believe that
Yu will come after who she hated.
How does that concern you?
Thank Your Highness for the advice.
Yu ought to reap what she sow.
But if there was a mastermind behind her,
she is most likely to come after whoever exploited her.
She will ask them why they used her as their dagger.
Your Majesty looks better today.
It is my duty to pray to the Mongolian Gods
on the first day of every month.
I feel much better owing to their blessings.
Your Majesty might not have been informed that
ghost stories prevailed in the harem lately.
Rumors should not be lent credence to.
The palace is never short of old wives' tales
for the past centuries.
An exorcism should be performed
if people take it seriously.
An exorcism?
Wouldn't that convince people of the superstitions?
Exorcism is not about convincing, but reassuring.
In that case, we will have the exorcists performing
day and night at the Baohua Hall.
Especially for the dead in the Cold Palace.
Their souls must be brought to salvation.
I thank Your Majesty for waiving my attendance
during the past days of my unwellness.
You look much better today.
I remember seeing your face bloodless a few days back.
I thank Your Majesty for remembering.
It is my duty to pay respect to Your Majesty daily.
I hope Your Majesty will pardon my negligence.
- Have a seat.
- I thank Your Majesty.
You haven't been too well since you moved in.
I don't have the heart to make you come every day.
Of course, it would be easier to come out during the day.
It would be too bad if you see things walking at night.
Your Majesty, it's thundering outside.
I'm afraid there will be a thunderstorm soon.
That will make it inconvenient to go out.
We shall dismiss.
I bid Your Majesty a good night.
Why didn't Lady Cao come today?
Princess Wenyi caught a cold.
She needs to stay with her.
I bid Your Highness Consort Fleur goodbye.
I bid Your Highness Concubine Beauté goodbye.
Lady Sourire has been feeling better,
but you still look very pale.
I hope you're not suffering too much from your nightmares.
Your Highness must not speak of it.
It haunts when you do.
How absurd!
You are out of your mind uttering nonsense to me!
Your Highness, please forgive her.
Sourire has been terribly scared.
In fact ...
In fact, many people saw it as well.
We have to be careful therefore.
Yes, exactly! I saw it too!
Why would Her Majesty have exorcism performed
if the ghost was just our imagination?
The ghost seemed extremely vindictive.
I wonder if the exorcists can control her.
The exorcists can repulse ghosts, can't they?
She must be bitterly resentful over her death.
"While the Buddha rises to one yard,
the Devil rises to ten."
I heard that when His Majesty gave her options for suicide,
not a concubine close to her pleaded her case.
That is why she had to
die grudgingly in the Cold Palace.
I would expect to hear those words from the servants.
What degradation it is
for you concubines to say that!
I apologize to have said that.
It's just that everyone has been in a panic lately.
Lady Cao is a very courageous person.
It would be nice if she was here tonight.
I wonder why she's absent.
Princess Wenyi caught a cold.
Lady Cao needs to look after her.
That is why she didn't come.
Lady Sourire has a sensitive nature.
I'm afraid you are overthinking.
Let's get going.
Certainly.
"A clear conscience
does not fear over a knock on the door."
Let's go quickly.
It's very dark now.
What if the unclean spirits come out?
It's about to rain.
We should go quickly.
What was that?
What was what?
- What was it?
- What's wrong?
(crowd shouting) A ghost!
She's here!
She's coming for me!
- Is it Concubine Beauté?
- It is.
Jinxi, report to Her Majesty.
Let's go check out.
A ghost ... A ghost ...
It's late at night!
What are you babbling?
Keep your mouth shut!
A ghost ... A ghost ... A ghost!
She's here!
She's here, isn't she?
Shut your mouth or I'll send you to the Cold Palace!
What are you waiting for?
Help her up!
Not me! It wasn't me!
The medicine ... I got her the medicine ...
I didn't ask her to poison Lady Sourire!
Not me!
She's gone insane.
Cover her mouth
and take her with me!
Hold on!
I hope Your Highness will reconsider.
It is not clear yet what has just happened.
I tend to think that we should send Concubine Beauté
back to her palace and summon the imperial doctors.
Why should she go with Your Highness?
Concubine Beauté lost her mind
and should not be seen in public.
It'll save her the trouble if she stays with me.
I would agree with Your Highness.
But I believe such an emergency must
first be reported to Her Majesty.
We have to act in an expedient manner.
I'm afraid her mad utterances
would terribly disturb Her Majesty.
We can report to her later.
I assist the Empress in managing the palace.
I believe I'm able to make decisions on her behalf.
This is a matter of consequence concerning
the head concubine of a palace.
I'm afraid His Majesty would be dissatisfied
that the Empress was not informed.
Don't you use His Majesty against me
even though he is very fond of you.
Are the two of you trying to find quarrel in a straw?
I have no intention of that.
Concubine Beauté claimed to be
implicated in Yu's scheme to poison me.
As a victim of the incident,
I have to do more than necessary.
Did you not hear me?
Take her back!
Her Majesty the Empress.
Peace and grace to Your Majesty.
Peace to Your Majesty.
All rise.
I thank Your Majesty.
What peace would I have when you all
cause so much commotion in the harem?
What happened to Concubine Beauté?
Zhou Ninghai, you are a servant!
How dare you put your hand on her mouth?
What an offence!
Your Majesty, Concubine Beauté
lost her mind and started to talk nonsense.
I asked him to quiet her down
lest she disturbs the other concubines.
But you must let go of her!
Are you going to walk her back with her mouth covered?
- Help me! Your Highness!
- What are you doing?
Yu came after me! Your Highness!
I didn't make her do it! I didn't!
Let go of Her Highness!
No, it has nothing to do with anyone else.
It was her own fault.
Don't be scared. It wasn't Yu.
Go with me quickly.
Yu is here! She's here!
She's coming after us!
Nonsense!
Help me! Your Majesty!
A ghost! A ghost!
You must stop talking nonsense!
It would worry me if you are to be alone tonight.
- Jiang Fuhai.
- Yes.
She'll stay at the Palace of Great Benevolence tonight.
Your Majesty.
It seems that Concubine Beauté is mentally ill.
I'm afraid she will disturb Your Majesty all night.
It would be better if I take care of her tonight.
Of so many chambers in my palace,
there is certainly a place for Concubine Beauté.
More importantly, she revealed involvement in Yu's crime.
This is a matter of great consequence
that I must investigate.
Do you not agree that I should stay with her tonight?
Of course it is appropriate
for Your Majesty to take care of her.
I simply wished to spare Your Majesty the trouble
as His Majesty entrusted me to assist you.
Otherwise, His Majesty would blame me
for being inconsiderate.
Your Majesty is the head of the harem.
His Majesty will be more assured if you investigate into it.
I bid Your Majesty goodbye.
Jiang Fuhai, bring along Concubine Beauté.
[to join mailing list] carsenwei@yahoo.com
[to sponsor translators] liberapay.com/ZHZSubbers
My Lady ... You're back, My Ladies.
Why did it take so long?
It worried us so much.
Xiao-Yunzi.
Sorry that you had to play the ghost.
I'm deeply flattered, My Lady.
But I did take a look at myself in the mirror.
That even startled myself.
You look much more than startling.
Concubine Beauté was so frightened
that she burst out everything!
I'm glad my little tricks could be useful.
I must thank Jade for making the costume
and Companion An for painting my big white face!
It was nothing compared to the idea
that you two came up with.
No, you came up with the brilliant idea.
We simply added a few more details.
Will you think that I was ruthless?
I did all this just to make us safe in the palace.
Why would we think that way?
We are sisters.
Will you, Meizhuang?
You have the most attentive eye
to have noticed that Concubine Beauté
was very afraid of ghosts.
All right, so much for the ghost.
Xiao-Yunzi, burn the costume.
We shall leave no trace behind.
Yes, I understand.
Your Highness, please have a seat.
You've been pacing the room all night.
Yes, that is all you've uttered all this time!
Cry, cry, cry!
What else can you do?
Why is she even here?
Your Highness, please pardon her.
She is sick and needs me to be around.
What use are you in such a crisis?
You can't even come up with an idea!
Your Highness, do you believe in ghosts?
It is because you don't
that they dared not approach you.
Concubine Beauté, however,
is not as strong as she appears.
That's why a mere ghost prank could break her down.
A ghost prank?
You think that was a prank?
Otherwise, why would the ghost approach
Concubine Beauté but not Your Highness?
It was Zhen Huan. It must be her.
Shen Meizhuang wouldn't
come up with such a nasty plot.
Very well, she dared to play a ghost prank.
I will turn her palace upside down
to find her prank props.
No, Your Highness.
Your Highness must not do that.
Your Highness is already under suspicion.
To raid her palace will bring nothing but trouble to yourself.
And Zhen Huan must have eliminated all evidence.
Your search would be of no avail.
So am I supposed sit there and do nothing?
Fortunately, Concubine Beauté has gone insane, hasn't she?
That is why she was talking insanely!
Talking insanely ...
How could you believe what a madwoman says?
A madwoman's words are not to be credited.
Peace and grace to Your Majesty.
All rise.
I thank Your Majesty.
I summoned you all so early in the morning because
I wish to know the details of what happened last night.
Her Majesty the Empress Dowager.
I bow in respect before Your Majesty.
Peace to Your Majesty.
All rise.
I thank Your Majesty.
Consort Fleur informed me
that Concubine Beauté is unwell.
I'm worried about her.
Why was the Empress Dowager brought into this?
It must be Consort Fleur's effort
to disentangle herself from this.
That was very bold of her.
The Empress Dowager is related to the Empress.
She will lean towards the Empress.
But Consort Fleur was the one who invited the Empress Dowager.
She had confidence in what she was doing.
But nothing she has can compare to a blood relation.
The Empress Dowager must not be pleased that
Consort Fleur has always kept the Empress suppressed.
In the wake of the commotion last night,
all eyes are watching the Palace of Great Benevolence.
But nothing really happened.
I heard this when I was a child
that there is always a calm before the storm on the sea.
Your Majesty must have grown tired of all these mad talks.
Please take a break and have some tea.
It is rare that I get to hear these mad talks.
You Majesty must not bear the mad words in mind.
I will have the doctors attend to Concubine Beauté.
There's no need.
Her sober words won't be any more pleasant to hear.
She will be sent to the Cold Palace
to keep your palace clean.
Yes, I will assign that tomorrow.
How useless she is to have broken down in fright.
It is true that a guilty conscience needs no accuser.
But Concubine Beauté said that
Consort Fleur was behind this.
So what?
That is merely her mad talks.
- Your Majesty ...
- I know.
Consort Fleur has quelled your authority
for all these years.
(sigh)
She never learns to know there are limits
ever since she was married into the family.
But the Emperor is fond of her,
and her brother is Nian Gengyao.
Now that Concubine Beauté is insane,
no one will trust the words of a madwoman.
Yes.
We will just send a warning to Consort Fleur.
You will say that the harem must be managed
by yourself to stop the rumors.
What if His Majesty ...
I will tell him when he's back
that you dispelled the rumor and pacified the harem.
As for Lady Sourire, she is very smart.
And Lady Shen is reliable.
You may have Lady Shen groomed for managing the harem.
Yes, they were both selected by you and His Majesty.
Announce my decree that Consort Fleur
will be suspended from her duty.
She will take a break from
assisting in the palace affairs.
Yes.
Jade.
What brought you here?
Greetings, My Lady.
Lady Sourire asked me to get some joss sticks
and burn the sutras she copied.
Ah, why did Sourire want to have the sutras burnt?
My Lady wishes peace for the palace in this time of chaos.
And salvation for Yu as well,
no matter what she did in her past life.
I should return quickly.
Please allow me to take my leave.
Certainly.
My Lady ...
What's wrong, My Lady?
Sourire copied sutras for Yu.
Does she blame me for what I did?
Why would she?
Lady Sourire is directly involved to Yu's death.
Don't overthink, My Lady.
We should go.
His Majesty the Emperor.
His Majesty?
Peace and grace to Your Majesty.
Rise immediately.
Your Majesty finally came back.
Have a seat.
Did you miss me?
I would always think of Your Majesty,
hoping Your Majesty was well during the trip.
I just visited the Empress Dowager.
She told me about the settlement of Concubine Beauté.
I feel relieved that you can finally put your mind at ease.
I hope Your Majesty would not
be incensed by the bygones.
Concubine Beauté avenged herself on me
because she cared about Your Majesty.
She cared about me?
Only she can tell whether it was me or herself
that she really cared about.
Even if it was because she cared about me,
I won't tolerate her for her malice.
I believe she has paid the price for the wrong she did.
Although Consort Fleur was
on good terms with Concubine Beauté,
I believer Her Highness wouldn't
reduce herself to collusion with her.
Her Highness is endowed with a resolute mind ...
A resolute mind?
What do you mean by that?
Her Highness is a determined, effective
decision maker in the palace.
I believe "resolute" can describe Her Highness
for her manner of managing the palace affairs.
That is a double-edged sword.
The Empress Dowager makes no interference
of little necessity in the harem.
But when she involves herself in,
it must be an intolerable matter of consequence to her.
Her stem punishment aims to clear
the foul atmosphere in the harem.
I humbly wish that there will be more
understanding and less begrudging in the harem
so that Your Majesty can concentrate on the
state affairs with peace in your backyard.
I heard your father coughing at court.
It seems that he caught a cold.
He has been chronically suffering from
laryngeal disorders, which worries me a lot.
I asked Su Peisheng to send him pei pa koa after court.
I am very much obliged to Your Majesty.
He is your father.
It's also my obligation to care for him.
His disease has never been less of a concern of my mother.
Almond lilly-root soup in the spring,
and steamed pear with fritillaria bulbs in the fall.
She's been taking good care of him over all these years.
They are a sweet loving couple.
That's why they have a sweet and loving daughter.
Your Majesty is even sweeter.
Mother, it is your death anniversary today.
I wonder if father remembers.
I wonder if he is ...
secretly burning joss paper like I am.
Mother ...
I am a useless daughter ...
I don't know when I will make a name for myself
and rightfully offer joss paper to you.
Who can it be at this time?
What is this?
How dare you burn ghost money in the palace?
Lady Cao.
You ... you are the maid of Lady Sourire?
You must know that
any ominous act is forbidden in the palace.
Burning joss paper is of major disrespect to His Majesty.
I'm afraid even she cannot save you from this.
I do beg your pardon, Lady Cao.
I promise this will never happen again.
I beg of you not to tell My Lady.
All right, you may rise.
I beg of you to pardon me, Lady Cao.
You are lucky that it is me.
You would be sent to the Department of Penalty
were you caught be someone else.
Now tell me, why were you burning joss paper?
Today is the death anniversary of my mother.
You are a very filial daughter.
But you could have offered respect
to your mother in the Palace of Pearl Jade.
Why did you have to come here?
I dared not.
You are the favorite maid of Lady Sourire, aren't you?
She treats you differently from the other servants.
Why wouldn't she allow you?
I dared not offend My Lady.
I beg of you not to let her know, Lady Cao.
I won't.
Clear the joss papper away quickly.
You shall not want to leave the slightest trace.
Thank you, Lady Cao.
[an account book]
1800 taels was spent on the four exorcisms.
[tael is a measurement like "dollar" today]
As it gets hot recently, an extra 32 taels
is spent daily on the mung bean soup for the servants.
Hold on.
The mung bean soup costs 32 taels a day.
What about a month?
That will be ...
960 taels.
"Wealth begins with frugality."
A bowl of mung bean soup can accumulate to
prodigious numbers over time.
I agree,
but that has been defrayed since the prior emperor.
I'm afraid the servants would complain if it's cut off.
I agree with Your Majesty.
The servants will work with all their heart for a kind master.
This is not an expense to be cut.
Lady Sourire, what do you think?
I know nothing about this.
I shall enjoy my tea while Meizhuang is doing all the math.
All she needs to do is enjoy.
Your Majesty, I reckon that the daily food ration
is unnecessarily high for each palace.
Take Noble Lady for example,
Every day, I receive 2 pt 7 oz of rice,
6 catties of pork, 6 catties of vegetables
[6 catties ≈ 8 pounds]
2 catties of flour, and one and half catties of toufu.
That is too much to ever be consumed within a day.
No to mention the rations for Concubines and Consorts.
I would suggest we convert the surplus food into extra stipends.
So the rations for mung bean soup
will be provided as extra pay for the servants.
That will make a saving from making the soup
and everyone will have a fair share
instead of quibbling about people
having more soup than they do.
That is a brilliant idea!
I can never calculate all that like Meizhuang.
(laughing inwardly) It's giving me a headache.
I'm thankful that Lady Shen
is helping me with the calculations.
Your Majesty flatters me.
I would have made all the mistakes in the world
without Your Majesty's patient instructions.
You're new to managing the palace affairs.
Practice makes perfect.
And you also have a natural talent for the task.
Your Majesty must be talking about my lack of talent.
Look at that!
What talent have we got
if she isn't counted as talented?
I would say that Your Majesty only has yourself to blame
for spoiling her to always speak her mind out loud.
I bow in respect before Your Highness.
Rise.
I thank Your Highness.
Tell the Empress that I'm here to pay my respect.
What? Did you not hear Her Highness's order?
That's okay. I'll see myself in.
Her Majesty is having an episode of cephalalgia.
She's not able to see Your Highness.
That is why I come to see her.
(emperor laughing)
(snort) She seems to be in a good mood.
Because His Majesty came to visit Her Majesty.
Very well then, it will save me
the trip to pay respect to His Majesty.
Peace to Your Highness.
It is of no consequence whether
Her Majesty is feeling unwell or not today.
What matters is whether His Majesty
will feel unwell when he sees Your Highness.
I believe Your Highness does understand
the consequence of that.
Why would you rather displease His Majesty?
(loudly) I bid Your Highness goodbye.
Your Highness, Lady Cao is here.
Peace to Your Highness.
The scorching weather must be
driving Your Highness into a temper.
I am willing to take any punishment
for Your Highness to vent out the anger.
You were just a girl selected from a hopeless family!
You didn't even get to see His Majesty when you moved in.
If it were not for my help,
how could you have a daughter and get upgraded?
Now I and Concubine Beauté are in a crisis
because of your fantastic idea.
How did you have the cheek to say all that?
I hope Your Highness will
enlighten me what I have done wrong.
I will take all the punishment.
You told me to preempt suspicion
by informing the Empress Dowager.
I don't care that Concubine Beauté
was banished to the Cold Palace.
But I lost my authority to manage the harem.
Wasn't it because you were
so up yourself with your brilliant idea?
I wish to congratulate Your Highness.
(snort) What is there for you to congratulate on?
Whatever Concubine Beauté uttered
were just considered as mad talks.
Whatever His Majesty suspected
could not be grounded in any evidence.
Although Your Highness is temporarily down from power,
you were able to keep yourself safe.
His Majesty has an affectionate nature.
Your reinstatement relies on
His Majesty's take on the issue.
Easy for you to say!
Now that His Majesty is possessed by Lady Sourire,
with the Empress placing barriers in the way,
I don't even have a chance to see His Majesty.
I will exert the utmost effort to mend
Your Highness's fences with His Majesty.
By what means?
His Majesty adores Princess Wenyi.
Rise. Give her a seat.
I thank Your Highness.
Concubine Beauté is as useless as a glass hammer.
But you are much more fortunate to have a daughter.
Unlike me, having no child to depend upon.
I am nobody in the palace.
Wenyi grew up peacefully under Your Highness's protection.
Your Highness loves Wenyi dearly.
She will be a filial daughter to
Your Highness when she grows up.
Look at you,
too immersed in the conversation to tend to your hair.
I was being hard on you.
- Song Zhi.
- Yes.
Attend to Lady Cao's hair in my room.
Yes.
I thank Your Highness.
His Majesty hasn't seen Wenyi for a while.
You should bring her to see His Majesty
at the Palace of Great Benevolence.
I'd like to,
but I'm afraid I'll get in His Majesty's
bad graces for my inarticulateness.
You don't have to talk.
You'll just need Wenyi to smile.
There is a phoenix hairpin on my dresser.
Put it on.
[translators] Carsen, Lenny, and Maxwell
[to join mailing list] carsenwei@yahoo.com
[to sponsor translators] liberapay.com/ZHZSubbers
Theme: The Lonely Phoenix
[phoenix is the symbol of an empress]
I dimly recall the colorful blooms in every summer.
They are as distant as the autumn moon in the water.
He loved me with a volatile heart.
And before I knew it, we fell apart.
Behind me are the promises and longing.
Before me lie the flute and the zither.
I loved you with my body and soul
But you hurt me from head to toe.
My wish ran athwart
and I ended up a fool of my destiny.
My love was the wind-swept flowers from a tree.
A plum bloomed in winter hoping for a fruitful summer.
But the irresistible winds of destiny destroyed her wish.
You can hear the flapping of a phoenix
but you will never see it.
What you see is the falling leaves from the phoenix tree.
The falling leaves from the phoenix tree.